A Guide to the Records of the Lyon Village Civic Association, 1926-1998
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Lyon Village Civic Association, 1926-1998
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 84
8 boxes.
Lyon Village Civic Association
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ditty Boaz, member of the Lyon Village Civic Association, in 1998.
Historical Information
Founded in 1926, the Lyon Village Civic Association is open to all those 18 or older who are residents of or real property owners in Lyon Village, a residential neighborhood in Arlington, Virginia. It consists predominantly of older single-family detached houses. Lyon Village is bordered on the northwest by Kirkwood Road, on the northeast by Lee Highway, on the east by N. Veitch Street, and on the south by Wilson Boulevard.
In the 1990s a controversial plan to introduce traffic calming measures aroused dissension within the neighborhood. Eventually the association persuaded the county to install such measures as speed humps and raised crosswalks. Neighborhood social life revolves around the Lyon Village Community House and the park and playground.
Scope and Content
Record Group 84 houses the records of the Lyon Village Civic Association. The collection measures approximately 4.5 linear feet, and dates from 1926 to 1998. Additions are expected. Types of material include bylaws, minutes, newsletters, correspondence, directories, printed reports, photographs, and clippings.
Minutes, newsletters, correspondence, and reports reflect neighborhood interests over the years. Major concerns were the building of Interstate 66, the Arlington Neighborhood Conservation Program, and traffic in the neighborhood and surrounding areas. Commercial traffic caused by businesses in nearby Clarendon was always a concern. Zoning issues included limiting group homes, controlling noise from National Airport, controlling height and building density in nearby areas (for example, the Olmstead Building next to the Clarendon Metro station), and preventing the building of large commercial enterprises seen as disruptive, such as a planned (and never-built) Home Depot store in Clarendon. Bulletins and minutes detail many activities such as weekend and holiday dances, parties and parades, and large celebrations for the 40th, 50th, 70th, and 75th anniversaries of the building of Lyon Village. There are many photographs of the neighborhood's Fourth of July festivities in the 1970s and of the construction and use of the playground next to the Lyon Village Community House.
Arrangement
Record Group 84 is divided into six series by type of material: bylaws, minutes, directories, bulletins, correspondence, and clippings; and into three subject series: alphabetical subject files, traffic study, and neighborhood conservation program. Arrangement within series is generally chronological, except for the alphabetical subject files. Folders containing photographs have an asterisk [*] after the file name. Folders with oversized materials have a double asterisk [**] to denote where material was removed and separation sheets added. Series 6, File 38, has both photographs and oversized material.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
RG 49, Women's Club of Lyon Village, holds materials about this women's club in the middle of the twentieth century. The records of other civic associations in the county can be found throughout the Arlington Community Archives.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Citizens' associations; Neighborhoods.; Community organization.; Lyon Village (Arlington, Va.); Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Constitution and Bylaws
  - Constitution and Bylaws, n.d., 1950-1994 (Box 1)
- Minutes
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes, February 1926 - September 1927 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes, October 1927 - September 1928 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes, March 1929 - February 1931 (Box 1)
  - Regular Announcements and Agendas, March 1941 - January 1949 (Box 1)
  - Regular Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, January 1945 - November 1947 (Box 1)
  - Regular Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, January 1948 - May 1950 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, September 1950 - May 1953 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, September 1953 - October 1954 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, March 1958 - June 1960 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes, September 1960 - June 1963 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, September 1963 - June 1964 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, July 1964 - May 1966 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, September 1966 - May 1967 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes and Treasurer's Reports, September 1968 - June 1979 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes, June 1980 - March 1981 (Box 1)
  - Regular and Executive Committee Minutes, June 1984 - April 1986 (Box 1)
  - Regular Minutes, March 1995 - April 1996 (Box 1)
- Lyon Village Directories
  - Directories, 1956, 1966, 1968, 1970, 1972, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Directories, 1978, 1984, 1987, 1990, 1994, 1997, 2000 (Box 2)
- Lyon Village Bulletins
  - Bulletins, September 1940 - October 1941 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, January 1950 - December 1959 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, January 1960 - April 1962 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1962 - April 1966 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1966 - May 1969 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1969 - May 1971 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1971 - July 1973 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1973 - July 1976 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1976 - May 1978 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1978 - July 1981 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1981 - July 1984 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1984 - July 1987 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1987 - July 1990 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1990 - July 1993 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1993 - August 1996 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, September 1996 - December 1998 (Box 3)
- Lyon Village Civic Association Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, January - February 1952 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, March - November 1952 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, January - July 1963 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, August - November 1963 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, January - July 1970 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, August - December 1970 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1990, 1996 (Box 4)
- Alphabetical Subject File
  - Airports (Box 4)
  - Fortieth Anniversary of Lyon Village: Correspondence and Program, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary of Lyon Village: Clipping, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Seventieth Anniversary of Lyon Village: Expenses, Photographs, History, Clippings, 1993 * (Box 4)
  - Seventieth Anniversary of Lyon Village: Correspondence, Proclamation, Participants, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Seventy-fifth Anniversary of Lyon Village: Program, Poster, 1998 ** (Box 4)
  - Antiques Show Program and Clippings, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Bulletin Delivery, 1978 (Box 4)
  - By-Pass - 13th Street: Edward O'Neill Files, 1961, 1996 (Box 4)
  - By-Pass - 13th Street, 1960 (Box 4)
  - By-Pass - 13th Street, 1961 ** (Box 4)
  - Cable Television, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Clarendon-Virginia Square, 1981 - March 1982 (Box 5)
  - Clarendon-Virginia Square, April - July 1982 (Box 5)
  - Court House, Colonial Village, Aurora Heights, January - August 1981 ** (Box 5)
  - Court House, Colonial Village, Aurora Heights, September 1981, 1994 ** (Box 5)
  - Entertainment, 1951-1989 (Box 5)
  - Fourth of July Celebrations: Programs, Photographs, 1973-1979 * (Box 5)
  - Fourth of July Celebrations: 1993, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Group Home, Fillmore Street, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Group Home, Hudson Street, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Home Depot, n.d., January 1995 (Box 5)
  - Home Depot, February 1995 (Box 5)
  - Home Depot, March 2-27, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Home Depot, March 29-31, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Home Depot, April 1995 - May 1996 (Box 5)
  - House Plaques, 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - House Plaques: Lyon Village Historic Castings, 1993 * (Box 6)
  - I-66, 1970-1973 (Box 6)
  - I-66, 1970-1973 (Box 6)
  - I-66, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Lee Highway Beautification, 1974-1977 (Box 6)
  - Neighborhood Day, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Olmstead Building, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Olmstead Building, January - February 1982 (Box 6)
  - Olmstead Building, March 1-10, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Olmstead Building, March 13-29, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Park/Playground, 1965-1972 */** (Box 6)
  - Parking at Lyon Village Apartments, Lots 721-725, 1964, 1981, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Schools, 1975-1978, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Signs for Lyon Village, n.d., 1977-1978, 1995 - May 9, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Signs for Lyon Village, May 14-21, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Signs for Lyon Village, May 22 - July 1996 (Box 6)
  - Veitch Condominiums, Patent and Trademark Office Plans, 1996 (Box 6)
  - YMCA, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Zoning, 1958, 1972-1981, 1996 (Box 6)
- Traffic Study
  - Lyon Village (LV) Traffic Studies, 1980, 1994-1997 (Box 7)
  - Lyon Village Civic Association (LVCA) Traffic Committee Agendas, Minutes, 1988, 1994, July - September 1996 (Box 7)
  - LVCA Traffic Committee Agendas, Minutes, October - December 1996 (Box 7)
  - LVCA Traffic Committee Agendas, Minutes, January - July 1997 (Box 7)
  - Traffic Project Management, November 1996 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Zones List (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Zones 1 & 2, 1997 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Zone 3, 1996 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Zone 5, 1985, 1997 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Zones 7-8, 1996 * (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Zones 10-12, 1996 (Box 7)
  - LV R.T.M. Plans, 1996 ** (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Plan Neighbor Feedback, 1996 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Plan Business Endorsements, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Plan A Ideas (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Management Plan and County Comments, 1996 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Issues, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Other Civic Association Traffic Committees, 1995-1997 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Plan, 1997 (Box 7)
  - LV Traffic Plan: Rough Draft and Ideas, 1997 (Box 7)
  - LVCA Traffic Calming Plan Revisions and Corrections, 1997 (Box 7)
  - LVCA Executive Committee Traffic Plan Papers, 1997 ** (Box 7)
  - LVCA Traffic Committee Briefing, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Baker Transportation Correspondence, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Notes for March 31, 1997 LVCA Meeting** (Box 8)
  - Notes for April 21, 1997 LVCA Meeting (Box 8)
  - Video of Ken Mobley at LVCA Meeting, April 21, 1997 (Box 8)
  - LV Bulletin Traffic Presentation Issues, April 1997 ** (Box 8)
  - Arlington County Board Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 8)
  - LV Street Classification Map** (Box 8)
- Neighborhood Conservation Program
  - Neighborhood Conservation Program (NCP) History, 1983-1997 (Box 8)
  - NCP, 1961-1977 (Box 8)
  - NCP for LV, 1978 (Box 8)
  - NCP for Ashton Heights, Arlington Ridge, High View Park, 1965-1976 (Box 8)
  - NCP, 1980-1984 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, 1976-May 1977 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, June - December 1977 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, 1978-1979 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, 1983 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, January - May 1996 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, January - October 1996 (Box 8)
  - NCP: Traffic, November 1996 (Box 8)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1966, 1973, 1981-1985 ** (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1986-1994 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1995-1998 (Box 8)